Guide to the North Star Mining Company and Associated Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Series VII. New York Hill Mining Company: The earliest document in this series is an 1871 certificate of incorporation. Most of the records continue until North Star bought the New York Hill in 1894. Within Executive Records (Boxes 24-25) is a full set of corporate minutes, beginning with a copy of the certificate of incorporation and the by-laws, including a copy of the deed transferring the mine from Alonzo Delano to the company (folder 599). The early minutes note the choice of bankers, the occurrence of assessments, and the embezzlement of funds in March 1879, by Secretary F. J. Hermann. An 1886 agreement between New York Hill and Grass Valley Water Company is copied into the minutes. Hague's investment in New York Hill is noted in the minutes in 1889 along with a revision of the by-laws. In 1894 North Star negotiated to buy the properties and assets of the company. The minutes are augmented by "copies of minutes and material from meetings" (folders 600-15). As in other series, these folders contain ballots from board votes, proxies, advertisements of the meeting, and copies of the minutes. Financial reports by the secretary for the period 1885-89 are also filed in these folders.
Little correspondence exists, the majority being letters received in New York Hill's San Francisco office (Box 24, folders 616-24) concerning assessments. Those sent from the San Francisco office (folder 625) are routine business communications usually noting the arrival of reports from the superintendent in Grass Valley. The last group of letters, written by the superintendent to the president (folders 626-27), are detailed, almost daily accounts of work in the New York mine from August 1885 to April 1886.
Information on the New York Hill Company stocks can be gleaned from several sources. There are a stock ledger and a transfer journal (Box 25, folders 632-33), both covering the period 1875-89; unfortunately, there is little information from the last five years of the company's life. For information on stocks in the 1890s, there are an assessment ledger and lists of stockholders. Although these documents were created for different reasons, they all supply data on who owned stocks, and their value.
Financial Records of New York Hill (Boxes 25-26, folders 648-70) contains a ledger, cash book, and journal for 1871-89, which all present similar information on company expenses. The ledger and journal are organized by account, while the cash book is chronological. Information on the company's financial affairs just prior to the Hague-North Star take over can be found in statements of receipts and disbursements for 1889-93 (folders 653-56), paid vouchers, and bank books. The statements, usually covering several months, are similar to the journal. Those for 1890-93 show New York Hill's President W. B. Bourn advancing money to the company.
Series VIII. North Star Mining Company: Although the North Star mine was established in 1851, the earliest records in this collection date from its incorporation in 1867. Over the years the company reincorporated several times, usually when new investors bought into North Star. In 1887 Hague became president and the largest stockholder of the North Star and used his position to invest in the surrounding mines. In 1929 North Star merged with the Empire and became Empire Star, which was then purchased in turn by the Newmont Company. Eventually North Star became part of the New Verde Mines, which sold the mines and equipment in 1958.
The records of the North Star Company are extensive and generally complete until 1900. Executive Records, which document decisions on development and finance, and Operation, Ore and Bullion, and Financial Records, which show how the decisions were enacted, provide a full history of the North Star Company.
Executive Records occupy Boxes 27-48. The minutes of the board meetings for 1867-87 (folder 673) contain copies of the certificate of incorporation, by-laws, list of original subscribers to capital stock, and the agreement by which North Star purchased quartz lodes and mining claims at Lafayette and Weimer Hills. Between 1880-84 the corporate officers of North Star did not meet. A new company, formed in 1884, eventually bought the assets of the existing company, but until 1887 two North Star corporations existed.
The new company's minutes (folder 674) include copies of many incorporation documents found in the earlier minutes. In 1887 North Star and the Grass Valley Water Company came to an agreement which led to a service contract. This same year a transfer agency was established in New York to facilitate trading on Wall Street. North Star's minutes often include copies of important agreements as well as lists of stockholders and their votes. The 1896 volume (folder 675) is similar to the preceding two volumes. The last volume, covering 1922-30, shows that the meetings are being held in Jersey City and later New York City. The volume ends with a series of printed and typed letters that document the merger North Star with the Empire Company.
"Copies of minutes and material from meetings" contains copies of the minutes, proxies, ballots, lists of stockholders, advertisements of meetings, financial statements, and important agreements. Material from 1897-1904 covers a period for which no official minutes exist.
North Star's correspondence (Boxes 28-43) has been organized by office and arranged chronologically. Letters from the New York office to the San Francisco office (Boxes 28-30, folders 715-43) were written by the president or assistant secretary to the secretary (for a list of North Star's corporate officers, see Appendix 1). Much of this correspondence documents the transfer of reports and information between North Star's offices. These letters can be useful in deciphering the company's bookkeeping practices. Although the president resided in New York, all major records were kept in San Francisco until 1898, when the New York office received reports directly from the Grass Valley office. In 1889 and 1895 Empire mine reports were enclosed in many North Star letters, suggesting that some tie existed between the two companies. The purchase of New York Hill and Massachusetts Hill in 1894 was probably contemplated as early as 1891, when the New York office asked for maps of those mines. Repeated mention of the Grass Valley Water Company in 1894 suggests that North Star was running the company several years before they formally merged. There is mention of a court case involving Scadden Flat in 1896, perhaps a title dispute. In 1897 North Star was involved with the Mount Pleasant Gold Mines Company. In fact, every major acquisition or deal in which North Star was involved between 1885-99 is mentioned in these letters (see also the later section Special Projects and Reports, Box 44).
Letters received at North Star's San Francisco office (Boxes 30-33, folders 744-90) are from the superintendent in Grass Valley to the president or secretary. They concern daily business, and usually report financial information or accompanying a report. From 1884-85 the lists of drafts, later kept separately, were filed with the North Star correspondence. Also included are letters from local suppliers and lawyers. Two frequent correspondents are Searls & Searls, lawyers on retainer in Nevada City, and McKay & Co, local grocers-dry goods merchants. Letters received in North Star in New York, after the corporate office was moved there, have been filed with letters received at San Francisco.
Although there are a few earlier letters, the daily communication between the Grass Valley and San Francisco offices begins in 1884. Superintendents report on machinery, such as the equipment received when North Star bought the works of the Scotia mine in 1884. Flooding in the mines in the winter and lack of water power in the summer were frequent topics. Letters in 1885-86 often touch on the tribute system, used in most Grass Valley mines. Emilie R. Abadie, superintendent 1886-94, was particularly worried about fires in the mines. Although he wrote long, detailed letters describing equipment and progress in the shafts, most of his letters consisted of a single line noting what drafts were drawn, bullion shipped, and sulphurets assayed and sold. In 1889 Abadie's letters mention labor problems, hinging on wage versus tribute reimbursement systems and racial tensions between management and miners. Although most of the superintendent's letters to the New York office focus on conditions at the mine, one gets a hint of North Star's corporate dealings. A series of 1894 letters by Hague to Jennings, in their capacity as corporate officers of the Magenta Company, suggests Magenta was one of the many properties acquired by North Star. There are scant references to Hague's interests in Cripple Creek, Colorado and the Anaconda mine in Butte, Montana (1895). In 1895-96 North Star was involved in legal battles over Irish American and Scadden Flat mines. In 1898 a printed letter from Frank A. Leach requests statistics for a publication by the United States Mint about metal production on the Pacific Coast.
Letters sent from San Francisco corporate headquarters (Box 33, folders 791-96) are from the president or secretary to the superintendent in Grass Valley. These are letterpress copybooks consisting of copies of letters in the earlier section "Received at Grass Valley" (folders 744-90).
Letters received by North Star's Grass Valley office (Box 33, folders 791-96) are to the superintendent from the president or secretary in San Francisco, from office staff, miners, and vendors. Many of the letters from the San Francisco office concern record keeping and what reports should be circulated. In the 1880s, renting or buying a mill and securing water power are major topics. A few letters in the late 1880s refer to the employees, some making derogatory comments about Cornish miners. There are hints of an association between North Star and Empire as the North Star president compares their expenses in September 1889 and asks Empire to cooperate on water expenses in 1892. During 1891-92 letters from the corporate officers and from attorney Fred Searls discuss James Kenney's law suit over a mining accident. In the following years legal problems arise over the Star Placer claim and the Irish American mine. The mid-1890s was a period of expansion for the company, and many claims and deeds are mentioned in the letters (see also the latter section Special Projects and Reports, Box 44). Power supply at North Star is discussed ever more frequently in the 1890s, becoming the overriding topic by 1894 as the company plans to build a new power plant. Electrical Engineering Company, Fulton Engineering and Ship Building Works, Pelton Water Wheel Company, Rix Company, and Risdon Iron & Locomotive Works correspond with the North Star superintendent regarding proposals, agreements, and installation of equipment. The collection also contains occasional letters from miners and engineers seeking work, and letters from present employees. Letters from miner's wives in 1895 and 1908 give some idea about living conditions and relationships between workers and the mine superintendents. Letters bidding for the North Star's sulphurets, usually from Pioneer Reduction Company, Puget Sound Reduction Company, or Shelby Smelting & Lead Company become common in the 1890s. From 1896 to 1904 there is a stream of letters from Fidelity and Casualty Company of New York, usually advising the company that North Star was not liable for various mine accidents. After 1904 North Star corresponds with other insurance companies. Letters of 1898 demonstrate that Arthur D. W. Foote is keeping the books for the Grass Valley Water Company, which North Star had absorbed. In the early 1900s, the majority of the letters are routine business communications from the office in San Francisco and vendors. In 1906-07 there are letters from the Grievance Committee of Grass Valley Miner's Union, No. 90 Western Federation of Miners ask for wage raises. Letters in 1907 hint at trouble between the North Star and Empire, and J. Ross Browne is called in to referee. A letter in 1909 from Mrs. Ballon offers to sell land to the company: "I was told you were buying up all the mines and mining ground you could get."
Letters sent from North Star's Grass Valley office (Box 43, folders 928-34) are from the superintendent to vendors and corporate offices. These are actually letterpress copybooks duplicating material found in the section "Received at San Francisco" (Boxes 30-33). Most are either routine business communications to the San Francisco corporate offices or about equipment to merchants. There are some financial reports which were enclosed in the letters. A 1894 letter seeks advice on hiring men "either on days' pay or Tribute." In 1895 almost every letter concerns contracts to build the power plant and hoisting works. A Grass Valley Water Company contract to supply Empire with water was copied with a February 1899 letter.
The Insurance section (Boxes 89-103) contains policies protecting North Star's hoist, offices, and quartz mill. These are organized by the year of signing. After 1895, the Stockbridge works and buildings are also insured. After 1895 the company takes out liability insurance against employee injury.
Accident Documents (Box 43, folders 936-45), dating mostly from the twentieth century, consists of paperwork involving the Department of Safety--Mining Division of the California Industrial Accident Commission. For information on North Star's reaction to mining accidents in the nineteenth century see letters concerning insurance in Boxes 36-40, folders 822-85.
The section Agreements, Claims, Deeds, (Boxes 43, folders 946-77) contains agreements, deeds, indentures, quit-claim deeds, land petitions, and many other documents transferring property and mineral rights to and from the North Star Company. There are also agreements or contracts governing labor relations and equipment. For 1896 there is a bound volume, arranged alphabetically, of tributer contracts.
Court Actions (Box 44, folders 978-83) contains papers from law suits involving the North Star Company.
Special projects and reports (Box 44, folders 984-1007), arranged chronologically by event, contains papers related to various mines, reports, or machinery. Many of these projects are also discussed in the North Star correspondence. A series of reports for October 1919 by "Operative #37" (folder 1007) concerns activity in the Central North Star shaft and at various miners' meetings. They give some information on unionization in Grass Valley.
Stock documents of North Star (Boxes 45-46) contain a variety of material related to stock ownership and value. The ledger, subscriptions, receipts of stock sold, transfer slips, assessment ledger, and various lists of stockholders record stockholders names, number of shares owned, and when stocks were transferred. Taken together they document the history of the ownership of the North Star from 1867-99, except for the years 1886-88. The assessment ledger notes when stockholders were asked to send additional money, but information on dividend payments can only be found in the financial accounts. The authorizations to buy mining properties (Box 46, folders 1033-34) note the need for capital in order to finance North Star's 1894 expansion. The letters to stockholders (folder 1035) also explain the company's needs, give a history of the mine, and describe the assets in 1897 and 1899.
Operation Records of North Star (Boxes 47-53) contain a series a weekly reports spanning 1884-1901 and monthly mining reports covering 1888-1901, each group recording different information. The weekly reports (folders 1043-69) track the quantities of ore extracted and processed, sulphurets obtained, as well as supplies used (wood, water, electricity) and men employed. This information is broken down to give details on ore costs in terms of supplies, men, and processing, and to trace the origin of the ore. The types of job (air driller, foremen, engineers, stokers) are also included. Most reports consist of a printed form with an attached handwritten narrative. North Star's monthly mining reports (folders 1070-1237) record the extension of the shafts and progress on the levels or drifts. This information is divided by company and contract/tribute work.
Other North Star operation reports are limited to a specific shaft or function, like tribute or mill work. Tribute statements for 1891-96 (folder 1240), arranged chronologically and then by tributer, record costs of milling and supplies (presumably services supplied to tributers by the company) and the number of cars of ore tributers extracted. The North Star mill reports (folder 1241) note supplies used and running-time of the mill, but only for 1898-1901. The Stockbridge shaft reports are a mixture of letters by the North Star assistant superintendent, pay roll lists, monthly narrative progress reports, supply lists, and other documents which together describe operations at the shaft. Finally, there is a twentieth-century map of the North Star properties and separate maps of the Champion and New York Hill mines (Boxes 53, folders 1246-47; Box 119, folder 2398).
Ore and Bullion Records, (Boxes 53-54) consist of the North Star Company's amalgam-bullion-sulphuret records and ore-and-waste records along with specific records for Massachusetts Hill and Champion. The amalgam-bullion-sulphuret records (folders 1248-64) report the value and quantity of bullion/sulphurets retrieved from ore (company and tributers) and processing charges. The second volume of each set holds summary statements. Biweekly amalgam-bullion-sulphuret records (folders 1265-70) were transferred into the above records and only lack the final bank values, shipping and refining costs, or net credit at the bank. North Star's ore-waste records (Box 54, folder 1287; Box 104, folders 2303-13), covering the period 1886-1903, report the source and quantity of ore. There are totals for the different levels, and company versus tributer quartz. These reports are accompanied by information on the lengths of the drifts and shafts.
Financial Records (Boxes 55-89) comprise the largest and most comprehensive set of records in the collection, although they only begin in 1884 after North Star's first major reorganization. Annual statements (Box 55, folders 1288-89) for the 1890s summarize the monthly statements. These annual statements record receipts and disbursements, representing the mine's operating expenses, and they include the office expenses for New York, San Francisco, and Grass Valley. The monthly statements tend to be more detailed than the annual and duplicates are filed with the superintendent's statements and vouchers (Box 55, folders 1292-94; also in Boxes 57-66, folders 1408-1502). Often, monthly accounts such as "statement of amount due by North Star" are filed with general monthly statements. The journals (folders 1290-91A) record similar financial information, but in more detail since individual expenses are listed. Moreover, the journals are keyed to the vouchers used to pay the bills.
North Star's tabulated statements (Box 107) were kept by Grass Valley for inspection by the San Francisco and New York offices in lieu of analyzed statements (see letters from New York to San Francisco, Box 28, folder 716-19). Tabulated statements, spanning 1890-99, are a series of expense accounts of mining labor, surface labor, mining supplies and materials, milling supplies and materials, power, miscellaneous, and tribute. Each account contains monthly entries and is broken down into labor costs per stopes and crosscuts, costs of individual material, cost of water for compressor, and hoisting. There are separate entries in red for Massachusetts Hill in 1896 and Stockbridge in 1897. In 1898 there are separate volumes for North Star and Stockbridge and one recording both. For 1888-97 the tabulated statements are summarized in yearly reports (Box 107, folders 2330-31). Analyzed statements of disbursements (Box 55, folders 1295-96; Boxes 108-09, folders 2344-58) list information on the expenses of ore production, waste versus quartz, tribute versus company, and supply and personnel expenses. There are two sets of bound volumes as well as duplicate paper documents.
Box 55 contains a series of North Star's specific accounts on tribute, the New York office, wood, and purchasing Massachusetts Hill mine.
Superintendent's statements and vouchers (Boxes 55-66) are a comprehensive monthly package of reports on the financial affairs of North Star's mine. Each month's report contains vouchers dated by when the bill was paid. From 1885-92 all the vouchers relate to the San Francisco office, but from 1893-96 there are some Grass Valley vouchers, and finally from 1897 all vouchers are from the mine. Starting in 1897 each month contains a monthly statement of receipts and disbursements, tribute statements, pay roll statements, and "daily returns of water sold to North Star" by Grass Valley Water Company. County and city tax receipts are enclosed in the November packages.
The last section of North Star's Financial Records consists of various documents related to drafts and checks. There are lists of the superintendent's drafts, checks drawn on the secretary of the company, the drafts themselves, and checks drawn by the secretary and president on the Bank of California.
Pay Roll Records for the North Star consist of the statements filed in the superintendents' statements and vouchers (Boxes 57-66, folders 1408-1502) and time books (Box 89, folders 1883-89). Time books, which are similar to the pay roll records, note the name, occupation, days worked, total days, wages paid, and rate per day. The list is divided into surface, underground, mill, central shaft, and improvement. The wage sheets, which span a few years in the 1920s, are organized by worker and record wage and bonus amounts.
Series IX. Rocky Bar Gold Mining Company: The Rocky Bar mine, founded in 1850, was taken over by the Mount Hope Company in 1856 and then by A. Chavanne & Co, which gained possession in 1858 when Mount Hope defaulted on a loan. The Chavanne company renamed itself the Rocky Bar Company and the mine was run independently until purchased by North Star during 1891-93. The records in this series date from 1863, after Chavanne had been in possession for several years. There are few Executive Records except for stock documents which tell the history of the mines ownership from 1863 to 1893. There is a 1865 map of the Rocky Bar mine and a financial journal for 1864-84 (Box 90, folder 1913). Finally, there are a variety of accounts, covering mine expenses, salaries, dividends, lumber, and other matters, for the years 1864-66 and 1870-77, written in the back of the stock ledger (Box 90, folder 1909). A history of the Rocky Bar starting with its incorporation in 1863 can be found in Box 90, folder 1908.
Series X. Tribute Mining Company: Tribute, located on New York Hill in 1879, was eventually taken over by North Star in 1896. There are minutes of board meetings for the entire life of the company (Box 90, folder 1915), as well as extensive stock documentation (folders 1918-21). Together these records tell the story of Tribute's search for a buyer and its eventual purchase by James D. Hague.